[Music]
hello everybody
good to be back on a new episode of ask
abajit episode 69 i hope you are all
doing very well as you know today is a
episode is an episode in which i'll take
questions from the comments that you
have
uh put in my
channel
so that's what we will be doing today
i wish you all a very good evening very
good day wherever you are and let's get
right into it
so let us begin with question number one
question number one is by vishal
apart from india as you mentioned often
which are the few countries which can
probably be major powers in the future
france comes to mind immediately your
take
so let's understand what's a major power
there are several categories of powers
global powers there is the superpowers
then you have
uh great powers then you have regional
powers and then you have insignificant
powers or peripheral powers so a
superpower is a nation a country that
can influence events in the world
anywhere in the world at any time of
their choosing so that's a superpower as
of today only the us is a true
superpower
when when we come to great powers we
could say china is a great power maybe
russia is a great power because they
have this
china has this economic might
and also
a regional military might
so it cannot influence things all over
the world yet at any time of their
choosing but they are trying to reach
that stage that status excuse me and the
russians have this enormous
uh
nuclear arsenal very powerful armed
forces and all that which makes them a
major
power now when it comes to regional
powers you have powers that can
influence things in the region if they
wish to india is one india doesn't do
anything to influence things in its
neighborhood but if it wishes to it can
so india is a regional power france is a
regional power the uk is in a way a
regional power even though it's actually
a wasall of the united states
and so on so these are the major power
that we have turkey is trying to become
a regional power or even a great power
iran you can say is a regional power
israel is a regional power and i'm sure
i must have missed one or two but there
you go so which countries can
probably become major powers in the
future well there are a number of
countries who have the which have the
potential in the next 20 50 years to
become major global powers india is one
china of course aspires to become a
superpower then you have france
you have turkey you have iran iran is
quite crippled by western sanctions
american sanctions and all that
it still aspires to become a great power
so
yeah these are the countries i can think
of so some people talk about brazil
because of such a large country and it
has uh
it has a good economy even south africa
some people speak about
australia well australia is not really
uh to be considered because it's another
country that's in the satellite uh orbit
of the united states
so uh i would say that
there is a higher probability of russia
india france becoming great powers
in the future i don't see maybe even
turkey
if they are allowed to
turkey is now hedging its bets it's it
used to it is still a member of nato it
was a u.s ally but now it is
it is moving towards china and russia
so the turk turks have their own
ambitions which are
not aligned with those of the west and
so on so these are the few countries
probably potentially potentially which
could become great powers in the future
uh
of course i hope india is one of them
and india becomes the one that
that it becomes one of the top three or
top four powers in the world in the next
20 years
sri ram reddy padmati has asked this 500
times at least so
okay so first before this there are some
people
who have this habit of
copy pasting one question dozens of
times please don't do that it's a it's a
humble request please don't do that it
it kind of clogs up the channel please
don't do that just ask a question once i
in the future if people
do that i will be forced to not take
that question just because you're
spamming so please please don't do that
i would like to take everyone's
questions i get thousands of questions
every week it's very unlikely that any
particular person's question will be
picked but i pick questions that will be
useful to everyone so please let's keep
it like that thank you
so the question is
uh please throw some light on how did
the nizam rulers manage to held or to
hold on to the deccan region of india
even though all the turkic rulers were
kicked out by the british
i am a resident of telangana and you're
being they have been glorified by the
secular government of the state please
throw some light on the atrocities done
by them in the region
well the nizams were actually the
original uh purpose of the nizams was to
act as administrators of the so-called
mughal empire which is the turkic mughal
empire right
so that is what their original function
was as the
turkic mughal empire became weak
and
it was no longer in power in much of the
country then these nizams became
independent and they became their own
rulers so they became the rulers of this
region of india
the south east region of india so that's
what they were ruling
it was essentially a kingdom a dynastic
kingdom there were i don't know seven
eight nine i don't know whatever number
of nawabs you can look it up online
okay all the information is there so the
nawabs were in power
because they were no longer uh
because the uh mughal empire kind of
became started crumbling
so
what were the atrocities they did all
kinds of atrocities are standard turkic
atrocities that turks have done all
across india the standard atrocities
were also done by the nizams if you look
at their wikipedia page i think they are
alleged to have donated funds to temples
and all that
very interesting very very nice yeah
wikipedia should never be trusted
remember that and if they donated some
money here and there's some temples it
doesn't offset the atrocities they did
so so why did the nizams manage to hold
on to this region after the turks were
kicked out by the british the british
did not kick any turks out
they kept the navaps of ours going on
in bengal you had some turkic people
some turkey rulers who were still in
power
right
and
in in telangana in southern india you
had the nizams who were in power
so that and and also you had the nawabs
of pataudi et cetera who were clients of
the british so it's not like the british
kicked all the turks out of india the
reason why these turks and the nizams
were able to hold on to power is because
they were of some use to the british
they
offered their allegiance to the british
and they said that we will rule this
region on your behalf we will collect
taxes on your behalf and we will send
the taxes to you and enrich you and you
can come and do whatever you want in our
region you can have your political
officers here you can have your rules
and laws that we will implement and
that's how it was done if after 1857
every single so-called princely state
every single king or queen or nizam or
nawab who hold held onto power was
simply a british puppet they all had
british political officers in their
court they were told what to do and what
not to do they had to implement british
laws not their own laws they had to send
taxes to the british
and everything was essentially
uh run in the british way
so they had very little power left but
they were simply in charge of
administration and they had certain
privileges that the british gave them in
exchange for their services
so they were simply clients of the
british and that's why the nizams were
able to hold on to power and after 1947
they tried to usurp power and
not become a part of india and in 1948
that was taken care of so there were
these terrible atrocities that they
unleashed on the
native population of the region they had
this terrorist army called the razakars
some of their descendants are now
politicians now you see that's how it
goes
so that in short is the story they were
the turks were never kicked out by the
british the british used
certain turks descendants of turks and
all these so-called rulers navarbs and
whatever else
as their own puppets to perpetuate
and spread their rule across india
adarshini says some people say that
india can never there are how many
questions like four three four three
questions i'll take one some people say
that india can never develop because of
the presence of a large number of
festivals or holidays due to the
celebration of different festivals every
year what's your opinion on this you
know what
you all i think if you are watching this
channel you know that india was the most
economically developed country in the
world before the british came in even
during the turkic era turkey occupation
of india the gdp was slowly going down
but did not it did not
get destroyed precipitately like the
british did it so
according to the research by the uh
economic economist angus meditation
medicine
india was the largest economy of the
world throughout much or most of known
history from 080 until until 1500 a d or
1780 or so approximately india accounted
for at least one third of the entire
world's gdp yes yes we know that
and before that india would have
accounted for at least a half of the
world's gdp that's how vast india's
ancient uh civilization was and that's
how developed it was i would not be
surprised if you if historic if
economists do a proper study and find
that india accounted for two thirds of
the world's gdp that's how massive this
this civilization was and that's how
advanced and developed it was
and we know
that there has been cultural continuity
in india for the past 10 000 years
archaeological evidence has proven this
without beyond any shred of a doubt
so we have had the same culture that we
have today in india for ten thousand
years
same festivals we celebrated
then what happened
in the past
why did the the celebration of so many
festivals not hamper india's economic
development
how come
that's the simple question you have to
ask yourself
right so my answer is very simple
everybody doesn't stay at home when
they're celebrating festivals you have
lots of different local festivals in
different parts of india
certain festivals are celebrated
throughout the civilization across the
world
like diwali and certain things like that
and those
are holidays
and then you have various local holidays
that certain people uh observe certain
other people's people of other regions
don't observe it doesn't do anything any
harm to the economy
it is a brilliant beautiful culture that
we have so many festivals
that people can indulge in partake in if
they wish to
right it is
it is a manifestation of the incredible
richness brilliance beauty diversity
and depth of india's civilization
so i don't know where these ideas come
from i'm sure it is the the school
teachers and college teachers and
professors and media etc who put this
into people's heads that india's ancient
festivals are terrible they're bad for
the environment they cause economic
damage to the country there's too much
uh
too many people going on leave and on
all that come on
look at the past ten thousand years of
history how did india become so great
economically etc technologically
scientifically in all spheres
how did it happen we had the same
festivals earlier come on think think
logically think think bigger don't look
at the world from a very narrow time
frame look at it from a big picture
perspective and then all your all your
questions and all your doubts will
automatically get cleared
swami dip says how valuable is it for
india that india wins the miss universe
title is it something to feel proud of
how does it help in women's empowerment
i'm asking this as i don't know what the
competitions are about but the social
media is full of it that's why i'm
curious to know about it and its value
and its importance
so how let's start with women's
empowerment if an indian girl if an
indian lady wins a miss world miss
universe miss whatever else
how does it empower women i'll tell you
how it empowers them it empowers them to
try to attain those
artificial cosmetic beauty standards by
using revlon and nivea
and and l'oreal
and all these western cosmetic brands
and to dye your hair and to to starve
yourself half to death to achieve that
that
weird supermodel physique shape figure
whatever you call it and so on
what is how does it empower women
i fail to understand
right so
let's understand why
the miss universe title exists
it exists it has sponsors it exists to
promote certain industries due to
further the
the
uh the interests of certain industries
mainly all these superficial industries
like cosmetics and all that right and
then various fashion brands and all that
so in the past you remember that
venezuela venezuela used to win the miss
universe title a lot
but in then about 10 years ago the
venezuelan economic economy crashed and
after that they have not won a single
title as far as i remember maybe one
maybe here and there but nothing major
like they used to all of a sudden so how
did this happen
and how does it coins why does it
coincide with the crash of the
venezuelan economy it's because they can
the venezuelan people are now very poor
and they can no longer afford these
expensive cosmetics
and so what's the point of promoting
their ladies and giving them titles
because they're no longer buying our
products
now india
at the turn of the century i think when
was it in the late 90s i think india won
a few miss world miss universe titles
etc etc some of uh our girls won these
titles it's when the economic reforms
had been done and india was seen as a
big emerging market so liaison let's
capture their market and let's let's
push our products there and now again
india's economy is again the fastest
growing economy in the whole world today
isn't it after the the slowdown of the
pandemic today india is the fastest
growing economy so once again they are
focusing on india and they want indian
girls to buy these useless cosmetic
products which
add a layer of extra superficiality to
you and that's it
and that's why they are doing it it's
all about marketing it's all about the
indian market they see india as a big
market of consumers
and that's why they are trying to woo
india and of course there's also the
woke signaling yeah i mean now this lady
whoever she is with the latest lady who
won the title she's going to go on a
world tour and spout all the same
slogans
women's empowerment and
green world
and whatever whatever is in vogue right
now whatever is the latest fashion
uh maybe she can call up greta thunberg
and take a couple of tips from her so
that's what it's all about and she will
happily do it because it it it
it
furthers her career in this
industry
right
i remember a couple of days ago on
twitter they were pushing her profile
here you please subscribe to this
please follow her she's somebody who
matters how does she matter who is she
so that's how it is so see that's the
reason why these miss world and miss
universe etc titles are given out handed
out to countries
uh
in the past when india was not doing
well economic economically during the
neruvian era the neherubian rate of
growth i think india won only one title
in like 50 years
or so
give or take
that's how it is it's all about money
it's all about the economy it's all
about the fashion industry cosmetics
other brands clothing brands and so on
so forth so that's the real reason
for doing this
okay this is a couple of questions josh
says considering the rich indian culture
do you think animation and games will
help indian culture proliferate
with the advent of web 3.0
and the second one is what are your
thoughts on gaming video gaming esports
in general do you personally play used
to play any video game how can india
enter the games industry and produce
games with indian stories like movies
and music games can also play an
essential role in influencing young
minds especially when games are played
usually played by teenagers and
youngsters can we make a world-class
game with excellent graphics and an
appealing story
you know what this is a very good ques
these are very good questions
first question by yash considering the
rich indian culture can animation and
games help indian culture proliferate
with the advent of web 3.0 certainly
see how japanese culture is probably
proliferated throughout the world
how did that happen it happened because
of their enemy and their games
so japan is a gaming superpower it has
produced so many so many various games
they have entire
uh companies that produce various games
uh they are the pioneers of the gaming
industry and they are also the pioneers
in anime they have so many interesting
uh anime series etc that people love
even though they are in japanese they
are all dubbed or whatever or we have
subtitles but the stories are very
interesting and they are really well
made and you will see elements of
japanese culture throughout all of these
things throughout the enemy series
throughout the games and so on and
because of this this is called software
this is how you
uh
use software that's how you build soft
power so that's why people have such a
very uh positive
uh
impression of japan that's why people
are so
interested in japanese culture
people have such a high regard for
japanese culture because of the way it
is portrayed
in
anime and in gaming and when it comes to
indian culture the reverse is true it is
portrayed so negatively in media first
of all india doesn't produce enemy we
enemy animated serials right animated
series and all that
and it's strange considering the fact
that most hollywood studios use indian
companies for their visual effects
special effects all that so india has
the technology india has the ability
india has the minds india has the
manpower to create world-class animation
and all that special effects and all
that and yet india doesn't produce
anything
right india doesn't it's because there's
no investment in this let's say somebody
has an interesting idea to produce uh
syria let's say someone wants to create
a new version of the
or a new version of the ramayana let's
say in anime form that's a long big
project at least 50 episodes i would say
or 100 episodes if you want to do it
properly and then
thoroughly
but that's a long project and who's
going to fund this there's no funding
available to this bollywood is the
funding but they have an anti-india
agenda
so you know that's that's the reason why
uh these things are not happening in
india
it will certainly help indian culture
proliferate worldwide if this is done
if indian animation studios uh are set
up it will not take a lot of investment
maybe a few crores
and this can be done it's very
interesting you need a wide range of
artists working together for this sort
of work but it will help india's culture
finally break free of the shackles of
bollywood and all the hindu phobic
establishment that we have here if
private companies can start this that
same applies to games
i've heard of a couple of games one or
two games that have some indian elements
elements of indian culture but
nothing much at all
so yes
it is certainly something that is very
important and it can certainly take off
i'm sure that indian kids would love to
play games that have an indian theme in
indian context and watch anime that has
indian context certainly and today the
thing is that the in the entire
attention of the youngsters is in anime
and gaming there's no doubt about it in
the 21st century in the second in the
third decade it's all going to be the
world of the teenagers the youngsters
generation z the zoomers right they're
gonna take over the world
and their attention is all online in in
web 3.0 like you say
in gaming they're all gamers they can
game on their mobile phones they can
game on big screens they have
playstations dvd i mean uh xboxes and
whatnot
so why doesn't india produce anything
that's the thing that's the that's the
terrible thing give me a 100 crore
rupees i'll do it
so you know what that's how it is that's
the reason why it is indian culture is
not proliferating esports is also
another interesting thing uh
what are my thoughts it's there
it is there it's the future embrace it
right i mean
people need entertainment people need a
diversion from their work from their
studies etc and this is the the thing of
choice it immerses you into a different
universe into a different world it gives
you a break from the world you live in
it's it's what people seek whether we
like it or not that's how the future is
going to be so we should embrace it
and i would like to see indian animation
studios and indian gaming companies come
up that produce some
uh original work that is indian themed
did i play any video games i have never
really had have the at the time to play
video games i was always studying when i
was a kid and later i was working so
i've never had the time i had a
playstation
i had a playstation i hardly ever used
it
so yeah i it's certainly interesting
it's fun as well i've played a few games
but uh not
very much personally
okay suyesh says
i tried to ask this question a lot of
times will i say it now um i'm an
aspiring filmmaker and science lover i
want to do something in the science
fiction fiction genre
can you please suggest in which
direction topic field i should work on
as hollywood is making science fiction
movies for many decades and it has
explored so much
what's left for us or what should our
approach be for science fiction
you know as a filmmaker you have to
unleash your creativity the truth is
that every story has already been told
that's the cliche in the in the literary
world in this in the film world every
story has already been told we have the
heroes journey
and so on so forth right and yet you
have interesting movies coming out every
year you have interesting literature
coming out every year you have
path-breaking sci-fi literature coming
up from time to time so it's all about
unleashing your creativity there is so
much you can do from an indian
perspective you can
if you're a science lover science
fiction lover you must have read lots of
science fiction stories novels etc why
don't you interpret it in a different
way
all these stories are set in the west
why don't you give them indian
characters and some indian twists and
try how it works
if i had the time if i was a filmmaker i
would have a thousand projects to work
on i would have to work on one at a time
and i would feel like one life is not
enough
so what you need to do is take an
existing
story
and redefine it reinterpret it give it
your own original twists which will make
it completely different that's what you
need to do and you have so many uh
themes from indian history from indian
culture
from indian civilization that the west
has tried to appropriate into science
fiction
right so we can
re reclaim these in in our filmmaking
so you can explore
science fiction stories with your own
interpretation you can explore even
fantasy stories you can go back to the
time the era in india when we had
vimanas apparently
and and
try and riff on that so there's so much
you can do i cannot give you a specific
idea that this is what you should work
on but this is the direction that you
should be looking at be original be
wildly creative
and reinterpret
the one story that has already been told
reinterpreted into in a variety of ways
you can up you can add lots of different
characters different different setting
different contexts different world
different time frame different era
different technology there is so much
you can do
unleash your imagination
and your creativity all the best my
friend i hope to see you succeed
akash asks can you please give your
opinion about the collision of the
titanic
some researchers say that a head-on
collision with minimal speed would have
saved it from sinking others say it
would have accelerated the sinking
what are your opinions on it considering
you're a physicist and this includes
ship's structural strength and velocity
well i haven't studied the causes of the
destruction of the of the sinking of the
titanic what i can say
conceptually is this
we we have some data we know this was a
new ship it was sailing from one place
to another point a to point b
it was in the north atlantic it struck
an iceberg a huge block floating block
of ice which is even larger below the
surface
and there was flooding in the ship and
it went on unabated and because of that
it
it sank
now here's the thing when you build a
ship a large ship for instance
you compartmentalize it
you compartmentalize
the hull
in such a way that there are lots of
sealed off chambers
in the hull the hull is long like this
and inside the hull there are lots and
lots of sealed off chambers so even if
there's a breech in the hull water
rushes in you can simply seal that
chamber off and the ship is fine and
then you can take it for repairs
this is how
ships are built
in the military in in cruise lines
etc in the case of large oil tankers
super tankers you also have this
compartmentalization because it was
observed in the past then when you have
a huge cavity in the oil super tanker
filled with oil then when the oil starts
sloshing
it can easily capsize the ship so that's
why they created all these small small
small compartments into which the oil is
uh poured and then that effect is
minimal and negligible even if there is
very rough weather and still the ship is
stable
so similarly in the case of
the breaching of the hull you have these
compartments i think the titanic also
would have had these compartments but
for some reason
there was something faulty with it i
don't quite recall it's many years since
i
studied this thing
but clearly there was some structural uh
problem that either the compartments
were not sealed off
or or they were defective and that's why
the entire ship got flooded and it
capsized and maybe there could have been
some
strength issue as well because we know
that the top hull fell off when it was
sinking
uh i think the ship was made of cast
iron or some some
it was a very modern ship for its time i
believe
um and i'm not sure if it if it hit the
iceberg head-on or if it was a glancing
blow most likely it was a glancing blow
from one of the sides the port side
starboard side i'm not sure but one of
these sides was struck there was a
longish tear in the hull
and for some reason they just flooding
went on unabated it was not sealed off
so that's what i can say about the
titanic it's a
there are there are many ships that have
sunk but for some reason this is one of
the most uh famous one iconic one
because it's it's been turned into at
least a couple of movies when i was a
kid i saw one movie from i don't know
how many years ago bought the titanic
there was not a stupid love story like
the like the newer one i'm sure lots of
people are fans of the james cameron
version i found it really boring first
of all the sea that they showed was
completely placid there was no it was
not choppy at all so it looked fake and
secondly they turned the whole thing
into a
fictitious love story which was really
boring for me from my perspective anyway
so yeah that's what i can say from from
a big picture perspective that
there must have been some defect in the
engineering of the titanic because when
the hull is breached you're supposed to
be able to seal it off and that's what
that is the main thing that did not
happen even if there's a breach even if
the material is not strong enough as
long as you can
breach i mean fill the breach by
sealing off certain compartments you're
fine
that's what did not happen
other says is it true that cuisines like
jalebi rajma chawal biryani mutton curry
vegetables like potato tomato onion
garlic apple and wheat were all brought
to india by outsiders you know if you
ask your teachers your school teachers
your college teachers the the so-called
professors in universities they will
tell you everything came from outside
india there was nothing in india we all
got everything everything of value
came from outsiders came with outsiders
they blessed us with blessed us with all
these wonderful things with their with
their superior culture they uplifted us
from our backwardness because we were so
backward indian culture is backward
and these foreigners who came to india
became indians they're not
foreign indian soil you become indian
and then they blessed us with their rich
superior culture
and all these wonderful things they
brought to india how true is this
forget about the culture where the
culture argument is different but
let's talk about biryani
biryani is turkic right biryani is
turkic it came from central asia
point number one
central asia is not a turkic region it
has been an indian region for thousands
of years only in the past thousand years
or so the turks took took over the place
and they conducted a genocide which has
never been recorded
all the original people were wiped out
the women were spared for obvious
reasons and today's
uh people from these regions uzbekistan
kazakhstan etc etc these are all
descendants of those women and the
turkic
invaders
right
so
central asia is not originally the
homeland of the turks the homeland of
the turks was far to the east
in present-day northern china
okay
so
central asia was an indian region many
of the things like possibly it is it is
claimed by some people some scientists
apparently that wheat originally grew in
the central asian region
and it and then in that case
india had
extensive contacts with the indians who
settled in central asia we know that
there were multiple waves of vibration
migrations outside of india
thousands of thousands of years ago
after the ten the the battle of the ten
kings and many other waves of migrations
and these people all centered uh settled
in central asia uttara madra uttarakuru
these regions were called right
and india had extensive contacts with
these people so if something new grew
there that would have been introduced
into india at that time not because of
the goddamn turks
right when it comes to tomatoes potato
etc these are
uh native to to central america to to
the americas not to eurasia so these
vegetables were introduced into the
whole of eurasia not only to india only
into the whole of eurasia by the
brutal spanish colonizers
of the americas so they went to america
they did whatever
horrors they had to perpetuate there and
then they brought back all these
interesting vegetables etc and fruits
to eurasia where they were planted and
then they become part of the staple diet
of of countries
across europe in asia
uh
potatoes
tomatoes chilies
uh the chili peppers and all that right
so the the turks had nothing to do with
this but before that also we had black
pepper which gives a very pungent spicy
uh
taste to food so indian food was always
the same
uh when it comes to biryani let's now
they say the turks brought biryani to
india
does rice grow in central asia
simple question if the turks brought
india brought biryani to india
they must have brought something that
grew there right
does rice grow in central asia if rice
doesn't grow to grow in central asia how
is biryani a turkic dish
we have had different forms of pulao now
they would call it biryani or whatever
in india for thousands of years we know
that rice is a staple in india it has
been a staple since the uh
saraswati sindhu days
so these are all lies they are claiming
these things without any evidence
whatsoever
what happens in academia is that one
so-called researcher
so-called researcher publishes a paper
which somehow gets accepted in one of
the journals this paper is going to be
without any evidence it's going to be
garbage paper but it somehow gets
accepted in some journal and then 15
people they cite their paper to make the
same claim and then five book authors
cite those 15 papers to further
strengthen the claim and then on the
basis of one
false fictitious incorrect garbage paper
an entire industry is created and then
this is accepted as fact that's how they
manufacture
data and that's how the manufacturer
claims and narratives
so do not believe this nonsense
uh
all these things much of these things
they are indian
in origin
i don't know about jalebi and rajma
chawal rajma again has been growing in
india you know kidney beans for
thousands of years chawal is indian
right
so
they're trying to say that your culture
is weak and inferior and it was very
thin and we got more things from outside
and that's how your culture is what it
is today ganga jamuni this is whatever
the hell that is don't believe that it's
all nonsense
why n says i learnt in convent school
what's a convent school a convent school
it's a conversion factory isn't it a
convent school anyway i learned in
convent school that and my history
teacher
used to mention that rajputs did not
like girl children and they were more
favorable towards male child or male
children she even said that small female
infants were killed in hot boiled milk
oh my god
it was not even mentioned any anywhere
in ncert books but she used to say that
without quoting any source there are
there were about 40 kids in our in our
class and she was a history teacher in
multiple classes year after year
different class new set of children
i think when i was a kid even i read
this sort of garbage in some mystery
textbook the rajputs used to practice
female infanticide
as a matter of routine
so then how did rajputs continue their
their generations if there are no
females
the thing is
this is a lie that has been repeated
thousands of times by our history
textbooks history teachers professors
etc
where is the basis for this claim
they say that rajputs used to drown
their girl children their infant girls
in water or milk or boiling milk because
apparently they were they were fond of
cruelty it looks like now let's examine
the the the truth about raj boats we
know that the the rajputs
were very idealistic they believed in
following rules in following dharma
whatever they thought was dharma they
forgot chanakya's dharma but okay fine
some of their leaders followed forgot
chanakya's
dharma for instance prathira johan so
they even were so magnanimous and
abiding to the rules that they would
even
allow their enemies
to
benefit from their mercy
even though the benefit even though the
enemies were adamas they were here to
destroy indian civilization and to
massacre indians and yet they would
uh
give them the same treatment they would
give to an indian so that's how
magnanimous they were that's how
dharmic they were in a sense right they
believed in rules they believed in the
maryada of the dharma and don't ever
break it because rules are rules and we
must be honorable
we must be honorable we must be virtuous
we should not be seen to be doing
anything adharmic that was the conduct
of the rajputs now tell me does that gel
with this narrative that they
must that they murdered helpless infant
girls their own children
a person who is that
dharmic would he do that
makes no sense makes no sense whatsoever
and where is the origin of this claim
where is it where is the source of this
claim where is the factual evidence that
corroborates this claim
yes in extreme circumstances rajput
ladies girls had to
self-immolate in johar when their men
went for the last battle in kesariya
against the turks that was simply an act
of desperation because they knew
that if they survived and their men died
they knew exactly what the turks would
do to them so they had to commit uh
suicide and actually incinerate their
bodies because even dead bodies were not
spared by the turks right
so that is a totally different thing but
because of this people have embellished
this by adding on this female
infanticide thing to uh
to the story so there is no factual
basis to this claim this is simply
something that has been done to malign
the rajputs
to give them a bad name it is completely
fake entirely 100 fake
samji says
the gupta empire had control over almost
the whole of india still one person
chose
not getting into any leisure lifestyle
staying unmarried sleeping in the most
difficult places around the himalayas
and much more just for protecting the
people of india and defeating foreign
invaders
would it be appropriate to call
skandagupta a real-life baahubali
maybe yeah maybe the thing is this
in the western world
in europe
kings
princess knights etc they enjoyed lives
of great luxury
everybody was a peasant everybody was a
surf everybody was owned by the by the
ruler by the aristocracy
they were the nobility and everybody
else was the commoners and they lived in
big palaces they had incredible luxury
everybody else lived in misery
that is what we have come to expect
because of our education system that all
kings are like this in india
kings were servants of the people
that's what they were
so kings had very one very simple
objective the king had only the king or
the queen or whoever the ruler is had
only one job only one duty to ensure
the long-term
security and prosperity
of the nation and the people of the
kingdom and the people of the empire and
the people that's what it was their
entire life was dedicated to this one
purpose
read the arthashastra by vishnu gupta
it lays out very clearly the duties of a
king the king doesn't get to sit and
idly and have leisure time the king
sleeps four hours a night and the entire
remainder of the period he is dedicating
himself to the service of the
civilization the service of dharma
service of the people service of the
empire
so
skanda kupta
while his actions are admirable he
dedicated his life to
defeating the shuita huna
invaders
the white hands
and he succeeded he made
a promise to his people that he would
not sleep on a bed and he would not eat
on a plate until his work was done after
feeding the huns he would sleep on the
ground on the floor
and they would eat on a plate and he
kept the promise and he defeated the
huns
now yeah that is admittable you can call
him a real life bahubali but that is the
duty of a king he was simply
fulfilling the duty that he was bound to
fulfill
so yes in today's world when you have
leaders
who are not leaders at all who are
actually serving themselves
if you look at india's politicians today
i would say
i would not say all
there are some really good ones some
really good genuine leaders but overall
i would say a majority would be
self-serving people
especially at the lower levels not all
again but some
maybe many
so in in today's world this looks like
an anomaly
array of light right but that is how it
was always supposed to be so skanda
gupta was fulfilling what's called his
raj dharma he was fulfilling his duty as
a king
and that's how it should be that's how a
leader should
conduct himself or herself
they just says who are the tushar people
in the mahabharat they are explained as
natures and they fought war on side of
the pandavas
they are said to be descendants of the
king
if they originate from ayati how can
they be lectures are they essentially of
indian origin at all what is the meaning
of lecture
this is a good question so let's start
with the concept what does lecture mean
lecture barbarian
the greek equivalent is barbarian it
means a person who is not civilized or
not civilized enough
in the old days the word lecture
was used to designate a person who did
not for follow the vedic lifestyle who
didn't know who who broke the
the the precepts of dharma in the vedas
even to a small degree if you do that
you are a mature that's how it was it
has nothing to do with
blood see the term i have used the word
barbarians in the past
and some people have commented that why
are you calling uh indians barbarians no
man i'm not calling indians barbarians
so so a person is not a barbarian
by blood a person is not barbarian by
religion
a person is barbarian by actions
by their actions and their lifestyle and
the thought process that goes on in
their mind and the ideology that
motivates them that is the only
form of barbarism actions is the the
visible
uh
output of all that is your actions
so a person is not a barbarian by blood
by religion only by actions if your
actions
are
adharmic then you are a mature that's
how it was
so now
with that in mind let's understand who
the tushar people were let's let's take
a look at the map i have to show the map
at least once in every session
otherwise the section is incomplete
okay so this here is the map
and if you go
like so in the past i have said multiple
times that there were lots of waves of
migrations of ancient indians vedic
indians outside of india north and east
of india sorry north and west of india
even east but that's not relevant here
and these regions were called uttarakuru
and
now if you go north of india over here
you have the uh
this region here
it is the tarim bayesian region this is
the taqlamakan desert it's now called
the taklamakan desert it's a turkic word
and this was the region of the tushar
people they are now called takarians
because they don't like to use the
sanskrit term tushar the west
so they have destroyed this term mangled
it and they call it tokarians so the
tokarians lived in this region
and as you say they must have been
descendants they are they're clearly
descendants of indians because when you
analyze their dna
nine out of ten of the ancient uh
remains you find there have the r1 a1a
uh
haplogroup which is of indian origin so
clearly they are of indian origin but
but it's interesting that many of them
have red hair and blue hair uh sorry
blonde hair
so they have indian origins but they
have some other ancestry as well they
intermixed with some other people i
guess
and they lived there for for a long time
so they were called tokarians where the
indian in origin well let's take a look
at their alphabet okay
let me show you
so let's take a look at the script with
the tokarians used to
for writing
so this is the tokarian alphabet
the vowel science the consonants
so this is a takarin script the
consonants go as kaka gaga
and so on which i think you all know
what it is
right
so clearly
these were an indian people and indian
origin people they spoke
a language
their language is classified as a centum
language not as a satan language which
would indicate it is
more western in origin but over here if
you see the script and the way it is
organized it is completely derived from
sanskrit
so you can see the indian influence
there so the answer is very simple uh
they were very clearly
yes there were very clearly people of
indian origin i think i'm back
so so that's the answer the tokarians
the tokarians where is the question
where's the question the tokarians okay
so the tushar people are the tokkarians
that the west speaks about today their
mummies are found in uh in the tarin
basin river region
in present-day western china
but
they had stopped following the vedic
culture properly they would have
followed it to some extent but some
things they had changed
and that's why they were classified as
lectures even the persians would have
been called lectures because then
stopped following the precepts of of the
vedas and they started their own new
religion or whatever what about
zoroastrianism and so on so that is the
definition of militias
they are mentioned that the tushar
people are mentioned in the mahabharata
and they are most likely the tukarians
that we find north of the himalayas
their remains are found today because
their culture is destroyed
what happened was that the turkic
invasions happened of this region
and all the entire indian origin people
were
defeated because they were too civilized
even though they were malicious they
were still too civilized
and the the
turks the huns etc were too militaristic
and they were focused only on conquest
and that's why they were able to win and
the turks killed off all the males took
all the women and the same story
which we see everywhere and their
descendants are the uyghurs who are who
still somewhat look like indians but
they also have turkic
features
so that in short is the story
okay next question
pink line cabs says how does quantum
mechanics explain
the reason behind smelling what's its
cause
so smell
the sense of smell
smelling
it is
a biochemical
uh
it has a biochemical origin
so when you smell something what happens
when you have
let's see a cup of tea a cup of coffee a
nice flower let's say you have a nice
flower
and i take the flower
let's imagine
this is the stem of a flower
and i take the flower it's close to me
or maybe it's far away but i can still
smell the fragrance of the flower how
does that happen how am i able to
perceive the fragrance of the flower
from a distance
it's because the flower the surface of
the flower
it releases
certain
substances
into the air
certain chemical substances into the air
which are fragrances
it does this for a certain reason to
attract insects which will pollinate
which will help pollinate it take its
pollen to another flower and pollinate
the flower that's the reproductive
process of plants
but this fragrance
these chemicals that constitute the
fragrance they disperse all over the air
and then they enter our
nostrils
and they settle on the bed of the inside
part of our nose on this on the surface
and that's where you have specialized
nerve cells that interpret each new
chemical signature as a certain smell
so it's a biochemical process same goes
with food you cook a certain kind of
food it has a certain smell it's because
it's when it's hot it's releasing off
this steam
and the steam also contains
another steam
uh the vapor steam yeah it also contains
other chemical signatures of the
constituents of the food and that
cocktail of chemical and
constituents let's say you cooked a
bunch of vegetables potatoes carrots
beans
coriander all that all of that combines
together to create a specific
overall
signature smell that you can recognize
the dish immediately from that so it's
when those uh
chemicals go into
the nose and they're analyzed by
specialized cells and they're that
information is related to the brain
that's how the entire thing is processed
and that's how the sense of smell occurs
and sense has a smell has a very strong
correlation with memory you may have
forgotten some memories but you if you
smell something that's linked to the
memory you will you can it can bring
back very ancient very old memories from
your early childhood etc which you had
kind of forgotten
so it's a biochemical thing
at the basis of biochemistry you always
have quantum mechanics but that
is not needed to explain how smell works
so good interesting question
pushpendressing says in your old in your
very old videos you gave book
suggestions for quantum mechanics in
dark matter while doing self self-study
in this type of topic how do you
overcome the difficult topics which
weren't easy to understand
is it maybe a weird theory quantum
mechanics is weird long derivations
complex mathematical models can you
suggest some tips to understand
difficult topics while doing self-study
in respect to fields like physics
mathematics engineering look when you
start a project you need the right tools
you go for an archaeological dig you
will need shovels spades
buckets
you will need leader and various other
newer instruments you need the right
tools and you need to know how to use
these tools
when it comes to physics
the tool is very simple it's mathematics
when you talk about quantum mechanics
there is a certain level of mathematics
you need to know you need to know linear
algebra you need to know differential
equations and many other things matrices
etc etc etc
you need to be
really proficient at that mathematics
otherwise there's no point studying
quantum mechanics
so that's the first step i would give
study your mathematics
master the mathematics master every all
the mathematics that's needed to study
quantum mechanics once you do that
quantum mechanics will become a piece of
cake then you will be able to see the
actual concepts and and work through
problems number two tip is solve lots of
problems
reading is a passive
activity
you want to
actually master a scientific subject
solve lots of problems that's how you
get your hands dirty and go deep into it
right number one master the mathematics
number two
solve lots of problems
and what else can i say
see when you're having a if you if you
have already if you've already mastered
the mathematics and you're good at
solving problems and you're not
understanding something there are two
reasons either your teacher is terrible
or the book is terrible it's as simple
as that if you're a good student who has
the tools to understand the subject and
you're not able to grasp something it's
because either your teacher is terrible
or your book is terrible
so if if you're doing self-study from a
book just get a better book
right get a book that's appropriate for
your level of understanding of the
subject master that book work through
all the problems then go to a higher
level
right so that's how it's done uh which
books to read i've given the the answers
in that book recommendation video
so that's how you should approach a
subject if you are learning from a
teacher
then maybe the teacher is is uh
not good enough incompetent get rid of
the teacher get a new one
right so that's what i can say
okay soham says
soham
is it true that albert einstein sold
stole stole sathandranath bose's theory
of relativity e equals mc squared
because bose and einstein communicated
only through letters and einstein if
einstein genuinely wanted to copy bose's
theory
there would not be any concrete proof
no albert einstein did not steal
so tenderness theory of relativity he
came up with that theory on his own
uh the special theory was published in
one of i think five papers in the year
all path-breaking groundbreaking papers
and the
general theory of relativity was
published in 1915 i think 15 or 16 15
most likely
but there was indeed correspondence and
communication between bose and einstein
what happened was that certainly not
moses came up with the derivation of the
quantum statistics which which are now
known as boys as bose-einstein
statistics so he came up with the
derivation on his own of these quantum
statistics
he sent it to a european i think
european journal for publication
and they rejected the paper
i think there was at least one rejection
maybe multiple rejections so they
refused to publish his paper even though
it was original and new and valuable
research so i think
because of this bose
uh
sent a letter to einstein with the paper
asking einstein for his opinion is this
paper good enough to publish will you
please kindly take a look because it is
being rejected so einstein read the
paper he was
impressed
what he did was that he translated this
paper which was in english into german
he sent it to the uh
to the publication annalender physique
which is a german publication very
famous
and he recommended that this paper
should be published
that's what happened
and then the paper was published but
then the tag einstein got attached to
the statistics so instead of calling it
bose statistics
people today call it bose einstein
statistics even though bose came up with
it himself einstein translated the paper
into german and sent it with his
recommendation to the journal and when
einstein recommends something it's done
so that is how bose was able to get his
paper published but unfortunately
einstein's name was added to his work
i don't think einstein asked for that
it's just what the west the western
world is like it's all eurocentric and
if an indian has done something there
has to be some contribution from
somebody from the west
so that's what happened but as far as e
equals since the square is concerned and
the theorem of the theory of relativity
that the quantum
theory etc photo photoelectric effect
all of that einstein came up
with these things
on his own
says
in some of your sessions you spoke about
the transfer of scientific knowledge and
calculus from india to the west via
arabian countries then why are arabian
why were arabian countries not able to
progress by leveraging the rich
knowledge of india
excellent question good
so it was the
so when the turkic
invasions of india began
these guys the turks the the uh
arabs turks mainly turks they noticed
that india had this enormous
bustling prosperous universities which
were like you know incredible places
with these huge libraries and so many
scholars and all that
and they noticed that there was
knowledge in india about very advanced
science very advanced mathematics
astronomy even uh
ayurveda medicology
toxicology pharmacology and the various
herbs and medicines and all these things
they were fascinated with it so they
sent their translators to india
scholars who who what they did was they
learned sanskrit and then they went to
the universities they requested access
they were given because we gave access
to everybody even to our enemies so they
got access to the libraries they got
texts they copied this text they
translated them into arabic or persian
or whatever was the language at the time
mostly arabic it was
and then they took it back to the to
their world to the uh to the turkic
islamic world let's call it now
and that's how so much knowledge was
transferred from india into the islamic
world and this is part of what is called
the golden age of islam
it was a renaissance of islam in which
lots and lots of new ideas came into
islam from india
it all these ideas came into the islamic
world from india
and then they built upon that
and much of it was just codified into
various books kitab al-hisab al-hind
they actually explicitly
gave the credit to indians that this was
all the work of indians but in the west
they have denied this they have tried to
to to make it look like the arabs came
up with everything on their own even
though in the original text they clearly
mentioned it's come from india so all
these so-called polymaths of the arabic
world islamic world were actually
translators
later on there may have been some people
who built upon that but all the original
work was indian hundred percent indian
so that's what's part of the golden age
of islam which lasted maybe a couple of
centuries look it up
then what happened why were they not
able to progress further by leveraging
the rich knowledge of india well what
happened was that shingis khan happened
shingis khan wiped out the kingdom of
harassment because they they behaved
badly towards his nation
okay so he retaliated and wiped the
whole kingdom out quarasmo is
uh
porsha and central asia the ruler was a
turk
stupid guy
okay and then what happened is that
ching is khan's after chinese khan died
his son
who um
his son what's his son's name
they can't became the khan and after
ogoday it was
monkey khan ching is khan's grandson
who became the khan now during the time
of monkey khan
what happened was that his brother hule
gukhan
funded westwards
and what holygood did was
he attacked the islamic world at the
time the center of the islamic world was
baghdad which is
now in iraq
he
besieged the baghdad
conquered baghdad and flattened the city
in the year 1258
and he almost destroyed the islamic
world he almost uprooted the foundations
of the islamic world
and after this the islamic world did
survive just barely
but after this
all scientific progress
all all of these
bigger things in life they were all put
on the back burner everything stopped
and the islamic world went back to the
basics military militarism
so all progress stopped after that
the golden age of islam came to an
abrupt and complete
halt to an abrupt and complete end in
the year 1258 with the fall of baghdad
to the mongols
so after that there was no progress in
they stopped
valuing
knowledge
they stopped valuing science arts all
that they went back to more fundamental
form of living and that's what happened
so that's why
they were not able to build upon the
so-called golden age of islam it was
destroyed first of all by this enormous
cataclysm the mongol invasion which they
were helpless to stop
and after that their entire lifestyle
and their
methodology everything changed
completely it got transformed and that's
why
they were not able to progress the way
they should have
okay the democrat says if mahatma gandhi
supported non-violence then why did he
want the indian soldiers to fight in
world war ii and world war ii world war
one and world war two
well mr mohandas gandhi
had very specific ideas about
non-violence
he was fine with indians
indulging in violence in service of the
british
but indians must not fight for
themselves that's that's the kind of
non-violence he wanted and
not all indians certain sections of
indian society should never fight
should never fight for themselves for
other for other countries for the
foreign occupier of india yes you must
fight they are our overlords there are
masters
we must fight for them only if we serve
them and are part of their empire will
they be nice enough to give us
a transfer of powers power on their
terms
and they will put their own people in
power in india and that's what continues
today so mr gandhi was very clear
non-violence is for certain sections of
indian society when it comes to
defending themselves then don't fight
don't defend just die
otherwise go and fight fighting for the
foreigners is great so how many indians
fought in world war two two and a half
million
two and a half million 25 black indians
fought in world war ii for a fight for a
war that had nothing to do with india
they fought for the british how many of
them died we don't even have the correct
numbers
so that is mr gandhi's
form
brilliant form of non-violence
user w7 says in 1971 with after pakistan
surrendered in the war why didn't india
implement a martial rule or power or
pakistan and reform reform its
constitutional military in accordance
with india's just like the u.s did with
japan after world war ii i've asked this
so many times all right
first of all let's understand something
in 1971 india
conquered east pakistan
and liberated east pakistan from the
punjabis
and then india gave independence to the
that part of india
but india did not ever try to conquer
west pakistan which it should have
right when they are so badly crippled
and so badly demoralized after army is
in our it has surrendered why should
india not have taken over west pakistan
as well and finished the entire business
once and for all
so india did not do that and that's why
they were not able that's why we indians
since we did not capture west pakistan
we were unable to
implement whatever you're saying
martial
law and the new constitution and
military and disband disband the
military or whatever we simply refuse
our political leadership
did not wish
to conquer west
pakistan that's part one and again we
gave independence to east pakist
independence in 1947
if you add 20 years at 67 so it's 24
years
bangladesh was not a part of india only
for 24 years we should have reintegrated
it with india anyway today we have
millions of bangladeshis running wild
all over india
so what was the point of letting
bangladesh become a separate country
india should have reintegrated this part
of india which has been part of india
for thousands of years it was outside
the country only for 24 years
we didn't do it
and we allowed those surrender
surrendered soldiers who had con
conducted a horrific
genocide in in
east bengal we just allowed them to go
go back home without any repercussions
that's what india did and again we could
have done some changes in the geography
of bangladesh for instance the
chittagong hill tracts
are not muslim majority now they must be
by now
the they should have been reintegrated
into india
at least that much we should have done
the chittagong hill tracts
those that's actually part of the
northeast northeast of india
there are no bengali speaking there were
no bengali speaking people there today
as we speak right now there is an ethnic
cleansing happening there by the
bangladesh army
they are
burning villages of the tribal so-called
tribals all the all the
people who survive are escaping to india
and living in refugee camps
and they are depopulating the place and
then
reconfiguring the demographics of the
place so what india should have done at
least at least this much india should
have done take back the chittagong hill
tracts that would have given access to
the northeast uh uh
states of india by by sea
we would have got
sea access to northeast of india
such incredibly short-sighted leaders we
have had in india and that's the reason
why india is in the situation it is
today that's all i can say
mano rama sahu says could you possibly
present an analogy as to why putin
vladimir putin walks with his right hand
stiff by him all top russian officials
do medve madhudev kasparov pavel durov
well
i don't know about the others madudev
kasper of
but i certainly know that putin has a
very distinctive way of walking when he
walks his left hand will swing his right
hand is always at his side it doesn't
move
what is this
so we have to understand
vladimir putin's background
he was a kgb officer he was a field
officer he was
stationed in east germany during the
cold war
at a time when tensions were really high
he was a highly trained kgb officer he
was trained in all kinds of
field activities which includes weapons
training and all that
and as
a field officer of the kgb
out there in east germany he would
always have had a sidearm a gun in his
in his belt or whatever concealed
somewhere
and the first rule of
of the of this kind of work
is your
your working hand the right hand i'm
assuming he's right-handed your right
hand never moves far from the gun
no matter what happens it should be
always next to the gun gun because you
may need to use the gun any time so they
are taught to walk like this use your
left hand in any way you wish your right
hand should be right next to the gun
it's called the gunslingers walk
and there is a habit that was ingrained
into him and on all of the kgb officers
and i suppose it has never left him
so that's why vladimir putin walks like
this i don't know about others i've not
seen the others but i can answer about
mr putin
interesting question
akash asks what are the chances of a
russian invasion of ukraine in the
coming months
what could be the
reaction of the us and could it
instigate the chinese to launch an
invasion of taiwan subsequently leading
to a world war see first of all nobody
wants a world war a world war is going
to devastate all economies nobody wants
their economy to be devastated neither
does china want that russia doesn't want
it the u.s doesn't want it so everybody
wants to avoid water to all costs the
question is what is the actual threshold
for war how far can you push things
until
you reach the line of no return and then
when we people have no option but to go
to war
and now we know what's going on in
ukraine there are russian troops
mobilizing and all that so people in the
west there is this big hysteria putin is
waiting to is getting ready to invade
ukraine and so on so forth so what are
the chances of
an invasion of ukraine
well you can never predict what goes on
in mr putin's mind
one of the
fundamental
principles of leadership
is this
never allow anyone to read your mind
never let on to others what's going on
in your mind always keep your plans
secret always be unpredictable so that
is a dictum that mr putin follows to the
t
his actions are unpredictable no one
knows what's in his mind
no one knows what his plans are
so
maybe this is a big bluff there is a
possibility or maybe he's actually
preparing to invade
or maybe he's trying to draw attention
away from something else there are all
kinds of possibilities
i would be foolish to try and read mr
putin's mind and predict what's going to
happen but let's
assume
let's assume a hypothetical scenario in
which mr putin gives a go-ahead and
russia invades ukraine they will
uh take or ukraine in a short period of
time they are overwhelmingly much more
powerful than the ukrainian forces
so let's say mr putin launches an
invasion of ukraine what will be the
reaction in china
i can guarantee that if an invasion of
ukraine is launched there will be a
simultaneous law invasion of
taiwan by the chinese because that will
draw the us into a two-front war the us
are duty-bound
to defend taiwan
and the ukraine also is one of their
some country that they have a great
amount of interest in because they want
to encircle russia
so
then the u.s will be in a dilemma whom
do we deal with do we split our forces
do we have can we deal with two wars at
the same time two very different wars
and very different theaters
so that is the case that could transpire
if mr putin is planning to invade
ukraine
we know that there is a quasi alliance
between china and russia we know that
there is a
significant cooperation and coordination
right now even though
the two nations don't really trust each
other but right now they are on the same
side because your enemies enemy is your
friend your enemy is the us
so
i can't say for sure if an invasion will
happen but if an invasion happens it may
be a sign that china will also invade
taiwan so
that's what could happen but will it
happen i'm not sure
because the u.s is still the
overwhelmingly
superior
power in the world it's the sole
superpower
it has the ammunition
to take on actually towards it at the
same time it will
if it if it goes to war
with either of these countries with
russia or china or with china or with
both it will it will have to take damage
it will take damage significant damage
in its own soil
so is that is it something the us is
willing
to contemplate is it something that you
the us is willing to suffer that's the
question so it's all about these
calculations you have to calculate what
the enemies position is what his
strength is
what their red lines are until what
level can we push it and
before they are
pushed past the brink
what is the deterrence posture so many
things have to be considered it's a big
globe-sized chessboard that we are
dealing with and these are the things
that the world leaders have to contend
with so
that's what i can say about this but
it's a very interesting question
okay rohan says please explain our
policy with fifth generation fighter
aircraft which india is planning to
induct in 2020 2030
why is it so hard for india even china
had has started mass production of j20
but here we proudly
inflate our chest saying amca will enter
production in 2030. is it worth a decade
of weight rather than simply buying from
other vendors when the geopolitical
landscape is pointing to a big big
conflict in the near future
look
india had a very good fighter aircraft
home
grown fighter aircraft called the maruth
in the 1960s
it was homegrown
it was our fighter aircraft and our
politicians killed it firstly they
refused to equip it with a powerful
enough engine
they gave it a substandard engine
and then
they just killed it off because they
wanted to
buy
fighter aircraft from other countries
because they were getting big kickbacks
big commissions for that
so that's always been the story if we
had not killed the marut fighter project
we would have been able to iteratively
improve the fighter jet create new
families of fighter jets from that one
original design and today india would
have had its own fourth generation fifth
generation aircraft india would have had
us
four or five different kinds of fighter
aircraft for different which would
fulfill different roles fighter
interceptor heavy bomber or whatever
else right
so indian
politicians did not let this happen
if that was done in the 1960s today
india would have its own fighter
aircraft multiple fighter aircraft now
today we are the same position right
we are building we have the pages we are
building a new version of the pages
designing a new version of these mark 2a
or whatever
uh we have the amca
fourth generation aircraft which is
which fighter aircraft which we have
which we are building we may have the
twin engine deck based fighter also
which is a derivative of the of the of
of these aircraft all together so we are
now starting the process of creating
multiple families of aircraft
now again if we say no let's not do it
because in the short term we can just
buy aircraft and let's do it that way
why waste money on this then we will in
the next 50 years again be in the same
position
imagine if india had not invested in
israel
and
designed and built its own rockets where
would india be today
india is today a genuine space power we
can launch our own satellites we have a
constellation of satellites that take
care of all our needs you don't realize
how important satellites are this would
not be happening without satellites
the indian military would not have eyes
and ears everywhere without satellites
the indian navy would not be able to
coordinate without satellites so because
we invested in israel that's why we are
able to enjoy this and we are not
dependent on other countries western
countries
for these needs
so it is imperative that india builds
its own aircraft fighter aircraft
india needs to develop its own engines
with foreign help or whatever doesn't
matter have your own engine
and have a bunch of aircraft two or
three different families of aircraft
which we can then take forth in the next
20 years we can even make better
aircraft fifth generation aircraft from
there i think the amca is supposed to be
a fourth generation aircraft which is
still fine it will have some stealth
capabilities there is also a flying wing
project
being worked on completely stealth
aircraft
uh so it needs to happen in the show in
in the interim period in the next five
years ten years we can buy a few maybe
100 fighter planes from somewhere
maybe there are false maybe we can set
up a production line in india if the
french are willing
so we can always incorporate foreign
technologies and all that into india we
can make it all part of make in india we
have to become atma nirbhar the late
general general bipin singh ravath was
very big on atman bharta
self-sufficiency he was pushing towards
that
he was trying to take the armed forces
away from foreign
purchases and he was trying
to make the indian armed forces
self-sufficient with indian weaponry and
technology that was the direction he was
going in his work was cut short let's
see how it goes in the future i hope it
continues but the story is very simple
we need to be abnormal we need to make
everything in house all our technology
we need to become a technological
superpower like we have always been and
then we will export variants of those
weapons to other countries
that's what needs to happen
short-term vision is always going to be
detrimental long-term vision think for
the next 50 years 100 years where does
india want to be in the time and then
work towards that
so in the short term you can buy foreign
planes foreign fighter jets for in
submarines why not
but in the long term we need to have our
own technologies our own homegrown
technologies that's what needs to happen
the chinese are producing those j-20s
and all that they stole the designs and
everything from the us it's not their
home-grown technology
in the early 2000s there was this
enormous
coordinated
uh chinese
hacking program
they hacked the pentagon the hack the us
department of defense they hacked all
the all their vendors
this uh this program was was code named
titan rain
so they hacked everything they stole
incredible amounts of information data
blueprints
uh trade secrets military secrets in the
us and they use those
to build their
fighter aircraft so the j-20 you can see
it resembles the f-22 rep raptor which
is an american plane it's like a
knock-off of that plane
the chinese have
stolen all the technology which i have
nothing against why can't india also
steal technology
in
in geopolitics there is no such thing as
ethics and morals there are no rules
whatever you can do do
so that's just the principle but uh so i
would say that india needs to be
completely self-sufficient in the next
20-30 years in terms of military
technologies and other technologies also
so india is pushing towards that i think
prime minister modi is also pushing
towards that it's a very very good thing
for the india for the for the nation in
the long run in the short term we may
have to buy things
in the interim period from one or two
other
foreign vendors
kingslayer lux says
should india
exit from the no first use policy
so what's a no first use policy it's an
it's a policy in nuclear deterrence
the no first use policy says
that i am a nuclear weapons power but i
will not be the first to use nuclear
weapons
if i am attacked
by someone with nuclear weapons i will
retaliate with nuclear weapons but i
will never initiate a first strike with
nuclear weapons even if i'm at war
so that is the no first use policy india
i think has a stated no first use policy
some countries
don't have a no first use policy the
pakistanis don't have no first use
policy which means that they are willing
to
be the first one to see to use nuclear
weapons
right
so the question is should india exit
from the no first use policy
i think the chinese also have no first
use policy the thing is this it doesn't
really matter what you say
it matters what you do
when when push comes to shove and you
are in in in conflict when there's a war
hey you can abandon the no first use
policy at that very instant and do
whatever is needed
right
of course there are entire military
doctrines built around such policies i'm
not sure if india has a stated military
doctrine
but
india obviously the military will always
have all calculations all possibilities
in mind
they will calculate everything if
required they will even ditch the no
first use policy i think it's something
that is used uh
more in diplomacy etc to an extent to an
extent not completely so it has a
diplomatic component that we can say
that you know we we don't believe in
violence and we have no no first use
policy that gives you a slightly higher
bargaining ground or moral ground
whatever
and so on so forth
so even let's say india goes to work
with china for whatever reason and if
the chinese are doing really well and
they are on the verge of taking some
strategically important territory i
think i don't see anything wrong with
india doing first use why not
i mean it's it's for the generals
it's for the commanders
it's for the highest level commanders to
decide this but in war there are no
rules there is nothing right or wrong
there is nothing ethical or unethical
whatever
you have to place the nation's interest
first
so if it comes to that india should
certainly ditch the no first use policy
and go over the first strike if required
it's all hypothetical of course
so should india have a stated no first
use policy i don't see any harm in
having a stated no first use policy
there's no harm it's just words are just
words always look at actions when an
actual war happens we will see
so until then words are words and don't
take it too seriously
aniket says what will be the
consequences if a nuclear-powered
submarine gets destroyed or has an
accident well to see the consequences of
that you just have to look at the past
history and see
what happened with other nuclear
submarines so for instance there were a
couple of u.s submarines who that
sunk that sank in the 1960s
thresher and scorpion i think they were
called two new nuclear submarines
uh so the submarines are designed in
such a way that even if the submarine
sinks its nuclear compartment is sealed
it doesn't leak out
and uh some submarines they they carry
nuclear torpedoes warheads ballistic
missiles icbms
so those uh weapons are also designed to
not leak out that nuclear fuel will not
leak out
they're designed to be watertight and
very compact
so um
and you also had a few soviet incidents
four or five of these kkk series
submarines in the 70s 80s there was a
k278 como somolets which
sank in the barranth sea
in 1989 it was a very advanced submarine
it was a prototype of some sorts but it
was fully functional or fully
operational
and there was a fire in the submarine
it was able to submerge some sailors
were saved but then it sank it's still
down there in the barren sea which is
north of russia
and there have been some reports that
some there is some leakage of nuclear
fuel or something cesium or something
was leaking out at a very small slow
rate
so
and then there was the terrible uh
submarine kursk disaster
another k-series submarine in the course
in the year 2000
uh so
so such accidents have happened in the
past but they have never had devastating
consequences typically the way you build
a submarine especially the nuclear
reactor the nuclear compartment it is
designed to withstand even a sinking and
full submergence of the submarine
and the weapons are also designed to be
able to just stay submerged and not leak
out anything
or dangerous
so essentially most
nuclear weapons warheads would have
plutonium which is extremely poisonous
it's a very harmful
element
so uh it's all built and designed in the
sense of
such a way that it will not be affected
even if there is an explosion in the
submarine for for whatever reason steam
explosion battery explosion typically
the nuclear
compartment is designed to be able to
withstand that
so thus far there has been never there's
never been any nuclear submarine
accident that has caused significant
environmental damage but it's always a
cause for concern so we know where those
shipwrecks are submarine wrecks are and
those are sites are typically monitored
periodically consistently so that we and
the radiation levels are measured in the
region so that we know if something is
going wrong in that case some action may
have to be taken but thus far nothing
like that has happened
aditya says what are your views on
japanese form of democracy they have a
prime minister but many experts say that
shinzo abe is controlling the government
and is still a major political figure in
japanese politics even after the
resignation
and most of the time japan is governed
by a single party either by coalition or
full majority so the japanese form of
democracy is something the the americans
imposed on it
after the
japanese defeat in 1945 in the second
world war the americans took over japan
they occupied japan they
allowed the emperor of japan to
remain the titular
and the constitutional uh authority
monarch of japan but they they created
this parliamentary democracy which japan
still follows they the americans wrote
the japanese constitution which is still
followed
and it's the it's a multi-party
democracy like we have in india
and
there have been lots of prime ministers
who have come and gone shinzo abe is one
of the major figures he has been
constant in japanese politics for a very
long time recently he resigned because
of health issues but yeah he's still
maybe the tallest figure
in japanese politics today and certainly
in his party
um
mr suga was the prime minister until
very recently has he stepped down
already i'm not sure
it's it's kind of hard to keep track of
the prime ministers in japan uh so how
do we understand what's happening there
see in any country
which has a foreign system imposed upon
it like india today india is not really
free today india has a foreign
constitution of foreign parliamentary
system westminster system which has been
put upon us it's not our indigenous
system of governance so we are kind of
under our foreign occupation even now
but japanese are still definitely under
foreign occupation under u.s occupation
the thing is this
in politics you have a stated head of
state stated leader prime minister
whatever and then you have extra
constitutional
power structures and power centers
this happens in every country not only
in
quasi-occupied countries like india and
japan
even in the western so-called
democracies
you have extra governmental extra
constitutional power structures and
power centers these are people these are
these are networks of people
who are extremely powerful
and at the top you have really really
powerful people whose power actually may
exceed that of the
the the country's government
and they can influence things in a
variety of ways while staying behind the
scenes this is not some conspiracy
theory this is what you see everywhere
if you look
closely
so even in japan you will have certain
power structures like that and mr shinzo
abe is the most powerful person even
today in his party
what what what causes power what creates
power what is power
power is all about networks the more
contacts you have
the more networks you have
the more people you can call upon
when needed
that is power
that is a force multiplier
so i am sure mr shinzo abe is still the
most powerful politician in japan he
will still have lots and lots of allies
in his party across the length in the
breadth of the country
in the municipal councils
in the counties everywhere so that is
power that is real power
and that's what gives you votes and all
that in in a sense
so um
so sometimes you have people
who control the government from outside
have we not seen this in this country in
india
you may have a prime minister who is not
the most powerful person there's
somebody else who's controlling
everything and who's the de facto ruler
this happens all the time so
is it is it the case in japan well i
haven't examined the case
what's happening right now but if it is
true well then so be it mr shinzo abe is
a nationalist
he he is a person whose stated aim is to
take japan to the next level and to
reform the constitution and make japan
more self-sufficient and more
militaristic because they have the big
chinese threat right next next door
so that has been his aim in life in in
politics in in
his political career and maybe he's
still guiding that to some extent to
some level or maybe to a large level
from outside the visible seat of power
it's possible
okay
krishna says
i was a devotee at a young age i was
very smart successful after getting
knowledge of bhakti yoga by
by somebody
my brain was very very fast in
intelligence after all these things
but my too much spiritual by my too much
spiritual knowledge i was popular in
coaching but then an extremely bad boy
asked me in front of everyone what if i
slap you
in front of everyone
will krishna save you
if no then cry and stop this nonsense of
hare krishna that was my last day of
coaching because i had no answer maybe
can you you can give me
i do have an answer
so you are a devotee of shri krishna
okay
and
this boy
us said to you that i'm gonna give you a
big slap in front of everybody will your
god will your great shri krishna save
you
if your god will not be able to save you
then shut up and get lost and after that
you stopped coaching because you had no
answer
right
so in the abrahamic religions let's
understand this the abrahamic religions
god is an external entity
one god a monotheistic god who sits high
in heaven judges everybody and on
judgment there they he will pronounce
whatever happens to us right to those
people who believe in that religion that
is the abrahamic concept god is an
external entity we and humans are all
born in sin we humans are sinners
and we should aspire to do good things
in life and then maybe god will forgive
us
that is abrahamic concept
now you say you have studied uh
studied what bhakti yoga etc job
meditation and all that
you have studied a lot of the teachings
of
your guru and shri krishna and all that
i suppose you were not taught this one
thing
in the dharmic world in the dharmic
concept
god is not external to us
there is divinity in each human being
why do we say deva bhava it means that
every guest who comes to our house has
an element of divinity an element of god
in him or her
that's why indians worship nature that's
why indians are compassionate towards
animals because there is god in each
living being
so now let's say this boy wants to slap
you
isn't lord shri krishna inside you
the problem is indians want to wait for
shri krishna to come back
one day
he made the promise that when things go
really bad for dharma he will come back
here's the thing
lord krishna is in the hearts of whoever
believes
in him and follows and walks on his path
so if you want god to act on the earth
on this in this world
god will only act through you
if you if you want god to change the
world
walk the path of god do the work of god
do the work of god of shri krishna
follow his teachings follow his path and
then you can say that lord sri krishna
is acting through me
so if somebody tells you i'm going to
slap you and will shri krishna help you
give him a punch in the middle of the
face and say this is a punch from shri
krishna end of story
okay
this okay
my procedure might be a bit incorrect i
came across a subreddit about shantidas
gosai
a hindu missionary
who converted
the maithi people of manipur to hinduism
and burned their holy text puya what's
the history of this so this is what you
will be taught in uh by your leftist
teachers which is all your teachers by
your professors your textbooks that
there was a hindu missionary bengali
missionary called shantidas adhikari or
he was a missionary he went to manipur
who could he converted all the people of
manipur converted okay what is
conversion converted the people to
hinduism and burned all their holy texts
that's the claim that is made
okay so the truth is this guy
does
shantidas
was a brahmana he was a bengali brahmin
gaudiya vegetablism
so now let's examine the history this
this episode happened in the year 1717 i
think
so there has been the presence of
hinduism of dharma in manipur for
centuries before that manipur is not on
a different planet it right it's right
in the northeast present-day northeast
of india
the whole of southeast asia was hindu
so there has always been a presence of
manipu of hinduism and money but for a
very very very long time now what
happened is that there was this king
called
he was in power in manipur as a king in
the
17th 18th centuries
and he was again influenced by by
dharmic concert or hinduism now look at
this the
religion the the people of manipur are
the metis the indigenous people of the
manipur are the metha people their
religion is called sana mahesam it's
always an ism in in western terms it is
a polytheistic religion very ancient
religion
it's not a religion because there is no
conversion there are no missionaries
there is no baptism it's
a spiritual
uh system
just like hinduism they also worship
nature they also worship their ancestors
they worship certain gods they have a
pantheon of gods and so on so what
happened is that this fellow shantidas
gosai
he
convinced
the king pameba
to adopt hinduism or gaudiya vaishnavism
gaudiya vaishnavism as the official
state
religion of the kingdom of manipur
kingdom of the kingdom of manipur was
much larger at the time it also
incorporated parts of burma which we
have lost today okay so he convinced the
king
to make gaudiya vaishnavism the official
state religion of manipur and then this
king in his
zeal went ahead and burned all these
holy books these ancient holy books
called the puyas and that is marked as a
great black day today
and now it has all been interpreted in
in the form
in the sense that they claim that
chantitas gosai came here came to
manipur
and converted everybody
and burned all the books listen
shantidas gosai wasn't a warrior
he was a brahmana
he was a priest
can some priest go to a foreign country
let's say a priest shantidas gosai goes
to afghanistan today
will he be able to convert everybody to
hinduism and burn all the holy books in
afghanistan impossible
it is the king who did that
there was already
significant elements of hinduism in
manipur there were already temples built
before that yeah and the king decided
that we should all now adopt gaudiya
vaishnavism because this guy is so
convincing
and the king went ahead and burned those
books it is not shantidas kosai who did
that but somehow they want to blame the
brahmin for this i'm not saying gosai
was a great guy i think it was a piece
of garbage for whatever he did whatever
but the thing is it is the king of
manipur who did these actions
right so
why is that not mentioned anywhere
and then later kings of manipur
continued the tradition of gaudiya
vaishnavism
and today's we still have the
significant elements of god devastating
which are very beautifully
intermingled
syncretized with sanamism in manipur
people
practice both elements of culture so
namazum they have tsunamism deities in
their house statues
idols whatever you want to call them
murthy's and they also worship sri
krishna
but today after
in the past 20 30 years this entire
narrative has been constructed in
manipur in other parts of the country
that this hinduism is uh
is an imposition upon the people of
manipur it was imposed by force because
apparently millions of people must have
been slaughtered really
so they say it was imposed by force it
is all brahmanism baraminical patriarchy
so down with hinduism and convert to
another religion and they don't convert
back there is no first of all gosai was
not a missionary there are no
missionaries in in hinduism and there is
no conversion to hinduism
the moment you start practicing elements
of hinduism you are a hindu there is no
conversion process
so these are all lies
and today people are being encouraged
encouraged to leave hinduism the maithi
people are being encouraged to leave
hinduism in manipur and adopt foreign
religions not salamis
for instance you had this sarita devi
the boxer she converted to christianity
a few years ago and such things are
going on so it's all part of a larger
imperialistic neocolonial agenda and
india's academia india's professors
india's education system is all a vital
component of that
and the media and the media of course
so that is the truth behind all of this
i hope it throws sufficient light on the
events
okay what shall we do let's take one
more question for today
let's take a couple of i'll take two
more questions
this was by ashna
if peaceful protest is a nonsense
concept
then how would a layman differentiate a
violent protest from a terror attack
um
okay
okay good question
let us imagine we are back in 1921.
today is 2021 december what is december
today december 18 18 most likely
this is december 18 2021. let's imagine
we are back a hundred years from today
december 18
1921 india is uh under brutal foreign
occupation british occupation
right
and mohandas the great mahatma
wants us to protest non-violently he
wants us to protest for the killah
movement but be non-violent
so ashna asks what is the difference
between a
violent protest and a terror attack so
let's say
some indians disagree with mr mohandas
and they
they acquire guns
and they ambush a convoy of british
officers
and and they kill five people five
british occupiers of india
that is called a violent protest a
violent attack
or a crowd of indians
demonstrates and burns down
uh the magistrate's office or a police
station because these are
uh
elements of occupation of india a
foreign occupation of india that is a
wire and protest who dies in these
protests
the elements of the occupation the
officers of the occupying power they die
in these protests people who are helping
the british
subjugate brutalize and occupy india
they are the ones who suffer
that is a violent protest
there are just causes of a protest when
your country is against foreign occupy
is under foreign occupation you are
fully within within your rights to kill
the occupiers in any way necessary there
is nothing wrong with that
so that is a violent protest what is a
terror attack
a terror attack is when you
attack
injure kill
innocent
citizens
a violent protest against the foreign
occupier will target the foreign
occupier
and nobody else
a terror attack will target the unarmed
and innocent civilian population it is
as simple as that and that's all i have
to say about this
okay one last question
what came first the chicken or the egg
i don't know if white people ask this
question but okay what came for the
chicken or the egg well neither came
first
what came first was dna the molecule of
life
if you look at any organism on
the planet earth
whether it is
viruses whether it is bacteria whether
it is single celled organisms whether it
is very low multi-celled organisms
whether it is tardigrades whether it is
crustaceans whether it is plankton
whether it is sea life or earth life
land life
or birds whatever
they all have one single thing in common
dna
dna is the fundamental building block of
life it came before the chicken or the
egg or anything
and that's the big mystery
what we actually are
we are carriers of dna our sole purpose
by our sole biological purpose in life
is to reproduce and pass on the dna
and combine it with the dna of other
members of our species
so what came first was neither the
chicken nor the egg it was dna and the
question is where did this dna come from
and that's the question of the origin of
life did it
spontaneously appear on earth through
some strange chemical reaction which we
don't know about
or was it seeded from elsewhere the
panspermia theory and that's why uh
that's why people are seeking now uh
scientists are seeking
uh science of life on mars europa titan
etc um
europa titan and some other moons of
jupiter and saturn where conditions may
be right for at least
microscopic life to be there so
in the next 20 30 50 years we will send
probes there we will analyze the the
atmospheres and the
environments of these planets if we find
any
any microscopic organisms we have to
first look for dna do they have dna if
we find dna elsewhere it means that dna
was
seeded into our solar system from
somewhere else
so that's what i can say so before the
chicken before the egg you had dna
all right
all right my friends thank you so much
for all your questions wonderful
questions very interesting questions
really enjoyed it
uh i hope you enjoyed it too
and
i will see you in tomorrow's session
live long
and prosper
bye take care